Guide to the Robert L. (Robert Luther) Duffus Papers, 1923-1970
Department of Special Collections
Robert L. (Robert Luther) Duffus Papers,
1923-1970
Special Collections M0203
Duffus, Robert L. (Robert Luther), 1888-1972.
10.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Robet L. Duffus, 1970 and 1973.
Scope and Content
A collection of manuscript, and various printer's proofs (galley, page, production) of the books of Robert L. Duffus. Also included are tearsheets of articles and New York Times editorials by Mr. Duffus.
ADDITION INCLUDES manuscripts of books, newsclips, correspondence (mostly to Duffus)
Biographical Note
ROBERT LUTHER DUFFUS
Robert Luther Duffus was born in Waterbury, Vt., July 10, 1888, the son of John McGlashan and Helen (Graves) Duffus. He obtained his A. B. from Stanford in 1910 and his A. M. in 1911. In addition, he was awarded an honorary L1.D. from Middlebury (Vt.) College in 1938.
Mr. Duffus was a reporter for the San Francisco Bulletin from 1911 - 1913 and editorial writer from 1913 to 1918. He then became an editorial writer for the San Francisco Call from 1918 - 1919 and for the New York Globe from 1919 - 1923. He has been a member of the editorial staff of the New York Times since 1937. Died, Nov, 28, 1972.
Among the honors awarded are the Chevalier, Legion of Honor and the Phi Betta Kappa Key. Mr. Duffus is an author with books including The Innocents at Cedro (1944), The Valley and Its People (1944), Non-Scheduled Flight (1950), Williamstown Branch (Memoirs) (1959), The Waterbury Record (1960), and The Tower of Jewels (1961).
Container List
- ADVENTURE IN RETIREMENT.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 263 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - b) Galley proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - c) Production proof; see oversize.
- THE CAT'S PAJAMAS.
  - a) First draft, typescript (some carbon) with autograph correction pp. 1 - 103, 123 - 150 (end) (incomplete); 21 pp. fragmentary drafts. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - b) Second draft, typescript (some carbon) with autograph corrections, pp. 1 - 123 (incomplete). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - c) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 165 pp. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - d) Page proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- JASON GOOSE.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 336 pp. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - b) Galley proof. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - c) Page proof. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- JASON POTTER'S SPACE WALK.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 135 pp. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - b) Galley proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - c) Page proof. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - d) Production proof. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    * e,f,g: see also: List of July,'73 ADDITION
- JIMMY'S PLACE.
  - a) First draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 242 pp., author's notation, 13 pp. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - b) Second draft, carbon typescript with autograph corrections, 269 pp. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - c) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 269 pp. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - d) Page proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - e) Page proof. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - f) Galley proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - g) Galley proof. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- NOSTALGIA, USA.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 103 pp. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - b) Galley proof, 2 copies. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - c) Page proof. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - d) Production proof, see oversize.
- QUEEN CALIFIA'S ISLAND.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 316 pp. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - b) Galley proof. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - c) Page proof. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - d) Unbound set of printed pages. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- THE POLAR ROUTE TO TIME GONE BY.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 196 pp. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - b) Page proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - c) Page proof. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - d) Production proof. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    * e & f: See also: List of July,'73 ADDITION
- TOMORROW'S NEWS.
  - a) First draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 202 pp. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - b) Second draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 140 pp. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - c) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 141 pp. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - d) Final draft, carbon typescript, 141 pp. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- THE TOWER OF JEWELS.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 216 pp. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - b) Galley proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - c) Page proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - d) Production proof; see oversize.
- THE WATERBURY RECORD.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 268 pp. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - b) Page proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - c) Page proof. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - d) Production proof; see oversize.
- WEST OF THE DATE LINE.
  - a) First draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 210 pp. Epilogue, 12 pp.; author's notations, 12 pp. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - b) Second draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 228 pp. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    (includes epilogue added to first draft).
  - c) Second draft, carbon typescript, 228 pp. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - d) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 227 pp. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - e) Galley proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - f) Page proof. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- WILLIAMSTOWN BRANCH.
  - a) Final draft, typescript with autograph corrections, 357 pp. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - b) Galley proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - c) Galley proof. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - d) Page proof, with autograph corrections. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - e) Production proof; see oversize.
  - Printed Matter and Tearsheets
  - By My Way - a series of articles of humorous commentary by R. L. Duffus, run in Nation's Business monthly from October 1948 to March 1956.Tearsheets. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- A FAIR PROSPECT. A series of 57 booklets of humorous commentary by R. L. Duffus, published as advertising for Nation's Business, April 1944 to October 1948. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, tearsheets, and whole number periodicals of items by R. L. Duffus. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1923 - 1924,pasted in scrapbook. (Volume 15)
  - Scrapbooks of Clippings of New York Times Editorials by R. L. Duffus.
    - a) September 26, 1946 - October 10, 1950. (Volume 16)
    - b) October 13, 1950 - February 5, 1956. (Volume 17)
    - c) February 6, 1956 - February 21, 1960. (Volume 18)
    - d) February 22, 1960 - September 24, 1962. (Volume 19)
- ADDITION Newsclips and Book Reviews re: Duffus. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Editorials written after retirement and Poems. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Tribute to Judge Learned Hand by R.L.D. Printed. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Miscellany (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Newsclips and misc. re: R.L.D.'s death. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- BOOKS
  - * JASON POTTER'S STAR WALK (later, SPACE WALK)
    - e) Typescript with autograph corrections, 135 pp. (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - f) typescript with autograph corrections, 131 pp. May 29, 1969. (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - g) 1 page of notes. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - * THE POLAR ROUTE TO TIME GONE BY
    - e) typescript with autograph corrections, 165 pp. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - f) typescript with autograph corrections, 196 pp. (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - ASHES ON A PROMONTORY
    - a) typescript with autograph corrections, 185 pp. (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - TLS, 12-26-72,Geo. P. Brockway to Mrs. R. L. Duffus - declines to publish. (Filed with correspondence)
  - THE DEATH OF ROSCOE CONKLING (1888)
    - a) typescript with autograph corrections, Mar. 30, 1967., 70pp. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - HOW TO BE 80 AND LIKE IT.
    - a) manuscript, Sept. 1971., 45pp. (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - b) TLS n.d. Donald Bean to R.L.D. re: mss. (Filed with corresp.)
  - THE LAST SARDINE.
    - a) typescript with autograph corrections, 222 pp. (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - b) typescript with autograph corrections, 222 pp. (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - c) typescript with autograph corrections, 216 pp., Jan. 12, 1970. (Box 21, Folder 5)
- ADDITIONAL MANUSCRIPTS AND TYPESCRIPTS:
  (The following 7 manuscripts appear to be early stories written during college)
  - a) A California Byway. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - b) The Two Kisses of Rafaelita. (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - c) The Silver Cord. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - d) The Story of the Abstruse Vagabond. (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - e) Drusiana. (written for a short story contest) (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - f) An Incident in a Garden. (Eng. 22; Oct. 1, 1909) (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - g) The Crime of the Knave of Hearts. (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Speech (Typescript). Middlebury College, Vermont. 1938.By R.L.D., with autograph corrections. (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - My Brother Bill (typescript) (6pp.) May (?), 1966. (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Typescripts of 5 newspaper articles/editorials. (Box 22, Folder 10)
- CORRESPONDENCE * OUTGOING (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Robert L. Duffus to:
  - BLIVEN, BRUCE
    - 1969, March 3
    - August 16
    - 1970, October 27
    - November 13
    - November 17
    - 1971, September 11
    - 1972, September 16
    - October 14
  - BROCKWAY, GEORGE P. (President, W.W. Norton & Co., Inc., R.L.D.'s Publisher)
    - 1964, December 12re: Adventure & Queen Calafia
    - 1964., Dec. 14re: Queen Calafia (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - 1968, April 15re: Jason Goose
  - DUFFUS, WM. M. 1995, April 5.
  - FORREST, WILLIAM P. (World Health Organization)
    - 1948, March 22.(R.L.D.'s reply - see Incoming corresp.)
  - KELLER, HELEN
    - 1960, August 26.(photocopy) (Reply - see Incoming corresp.)
  - MERRILL, REV. CHARLES C.
    - 1957, August 22.(Reply - see Incoming corresp.)
  - OLDER, FREMONT
    - 1920, June 21.
  - SULZBERGER, ARTHUR HAYS (Publisher, N.Y. Times)
    - 1962, January 19(Reply - see Incoming corresp.)
  - VILLA, MRS. MARION
    - 1969, June 21
    - 1970, February 25
- CORRESPONDENCE * INCOMING
  - ADLER, RUTH (Editor of Times Talk) (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - 1967, March 6.re: article on Otto Tolischus.
  - ALLEN, WARNER M.
    - 1948, March 22.re: Fair Prospects.
  - ALPHAND, HERVÉ (French Ambassador to the U.S.)
    - 1958, June 19.re: article The Other France and poem, The Map of France. (In French).
  - AMRINE, MABEL CHILCOTT
    - 1958, October 18.
  - ANDERSON, MAXWELL
    - 1948, February 28.
  - ANGELL, ORSON (Director of Advertising for Nation's Business)
    - 1948, March 2.re: survey of popularity of A Fair Prospect.
      - 3 Enclosures: J. D. Ford (Weirton Steel Co.) to Ms. Vera Lundquist of the Nation's Business Survey, W. Stanley Pearce (Fireman's Fund Insurance Co.) to V. L.
      - Robert F. Wood (the Autocar Co.) to V. L.
    - 1948, March 8.re: R.L.D.'s fan mail re: A Fair Prospect.
      - 3 Enclosures: Edward A. Daubenspeck (Chamber of Commerce, Shelby, Montana).
      - J. T. Ruble (Clay County Chamber of Commerce, West Point, Mississippi).
      - John P. Taylor (RCA).
    - 1972, August 30.
  - ATKINSON, BROOKS. 1962, Oct. 2., TLS.
  - BEAN, DONALD
    - n.d.Included with mss. How to be 80 and Like It. (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - BLADES, LESLIE BURTON
    - 1966, August 3.re: Adventures in Retirement.
  - BLIVEN, BRUCE
    - 1969, March 2re: Jason Goose.
    - 1970, January 25.re: The Polar Route.
    - 1970, October 15.re: Jason Potter's Space Walk with clip.
    - 1972, April 18.re: The Santa Fe Trail.
  - BORLAND, HAL (and Barbara)
    - 1970, February 8.
    - 1970, August 26.with tearsheet re: Jason Potter's Space Walk.
    - 1970, August 29.re: Flag Day editorial.
    - 1972, November 24.
  - BROCKWAY, GEORGE P. (President, W. W. Norton & Co., Inc., R.L.D.'s publisher) (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - 1964, December 10.re: The Island of Queen Calafia; Adventures...
    - 1964, December 18.
    - 1964, December 28.
    - 1965, June 24re: Queen Calafia.
    - 1965, September 30.re: Jimmy's Place.
    - 1965, October 6.
    - 1965, December 6.
    - 1968, May 1re: Jason Goose.
    - 1968, May 6.
    - 1969, January 13.
    - 1969, December 31.
    - 1970, January 7.
    - 1971, April 22.re: The Last Sardine.
    - 1971, May 25.
    - 1972, September 22.[To Mrs. R.L. Duffus]
    - 1972, December 26.[To Mrs. R. L. Duffus]
  - BURKE, SHIRLEY
    - 1942, January 4.re: Treasury Star Parade radio program. (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - CHANDLER, R. K.
    - 1958, November 27.re: Williamstown Branch.
  - CORBALLY, WINIFRED
    - 1964, June 25, (photocopy)
    - 1966, June 24., (photocopy)
    - See also: KELLER, HELEN.
  - COWDRY, MRS. E. VINCENT
    - N. D.ALS (to Leah Louise).
  - [CRANE], CHARLES
    - 1959, October 27.
    - [1959], December 24.
  - DAVIS, H. L.
    - 1957, June 7.(mention of Clifford Irving).
  - DODDS, JOHN W.
    - 1970, June 29.re: The Polar Route...
    - 1971, May 10.re: Tomorros's News.
  - DORFMAN, JOSEPH. (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - 1971, July 12., TLS
  - DUFFUS, WILLIAM M. (Brother of R.L.D.) (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - 1966, January 21.
    - 1966, February 4.
  - EISENHOWER, DWIGHT D. (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - 1957, December 3.re: editorial R.L.D. wrote about him. with clips.
  - FONTANA, JOHN
    - 1971, February 8.re: Williamstown Branch.
  - FORREST, WILLIAM P. (World Health Organization)
    - 1948, March 19.(with reply by R.L.D. - Outgoing corresp.)
  - FRANCESCHI, ESTHER SEAVER (MRS. A. G.)
    - 1959, February 5.re: Williamstown Branch.
  - Friedlander, [Paul?]
    - 1963, Oct. 2., TLS.
  - GALPIN, PERRIN C. (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - 1959, October 26.re: Waterbury Record.
  - GERMOND, PETER
    - 1948, March 6.re: A Fair Prospect.
  - GLEASON, EDGAR T. (Scoop)
    - 1959, March 31.
  - GRUENING, ERNEST.
    - [1965, Dec. 4]., ALS.
  - HADDOCK, CONSTANCE M. (MRS. G. T.)
    - 1969, February 23.
  - HAYDEN, HIRAM.
    - 1948, March 19.
  - HOUGH, HENRY BEETLE
    - 1969, December 17.
    - 1970, August 24.
    - 1971, Dec. 29
    - 1972, June 3.
  - INGRAM, K. C.
    - 1948, February 5.
  - KAYE, FRANK M.
    - 1966, October 12.
  - KELLER, HELEN (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - 1960, August 23., (photocopy)
      (with reply - Outgoing corresp.)
    - 1960, May 12., (photocopy)
    - See also: CORBALLY, WINIFRED.
  - KREHBIEL, EDWARD
    - 1948, March 17.
  - LA GUARDIA, FIORELLO H. (Mayor of New York).
    - 1941, December 29.re: article on La Gaurdia to be written by R.L.D.
  - LAMPSON, ROBIN
    - 1968, May 5.
  - LEAVITT, RAY (S. F. Press Club) (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - 1968, April 5.
    - 1968, April 12.
  - LILIENTHAL, DAVID E.
    - 1959, May 25.
    - 1965, Feb. 9.re: Adventure in Retirement
  - LOWRY, HELEN (sister)
    - 1959, December 10.re: Robert Aura Smith.
  - MANN, LUCY (MRS. WILLIAM M.) (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - ---- October 22.
  - MASLIN, MARSH
    - ---- May 24.
  - MERRIL, REV. CHARLES C.
    - 1957, August 15.(with reply - Outgoing corresp.)
  - MERZ, CHARLES
    - 1961, April 26.Memo.
    - 1966, March 26.re: death of R.L.D.'s brother (William M.?]
  - MOULTON, ELLA SIBLEY (MRS. WILLARD A.)
    - 1958, December 14.
  - OAKES, JOHN B.
    - n.d.Memo re: Pulitzer Prize
  - ORTON, LARRY M.
    - 1963, Oct. 6., TLS
  - PATTERSON, Wm. D.
    - 1962, Oct. 9., TLS
  - PRESCOTT, ORVILLE
    - 1964, December 29.
  - PROFFITT, CHARLES G.
    - 1963, Jan. 28., TLS
  - RABINOWITZ, AARON
    - 1970, Oct. 25, TLS
  - RICHEY, PAUL
    - 1948, March 4.re: A Fair Prospect - copy enclosed with missing pages.
  - ROBINSON, BELLE D.
    - 1958, November 29.
  - SANDBURG, CARL (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - 1935, February 19.re: ref. to Mark Sullivan as historian; re: Sandburg's actions in 1898 as U.S. volunteer in Puerto Rico engaged in driving out the Madrid government.
    - 1943, July 15.re: R.L.D.'s Lincoln Poem entitled Feb. 12, 1863.with cvr.
    - 1960, Dec. 7.re: R.L.D.'s The Tower of Jewels., TLS
  - SHANNON, WILLIAM V.
    - 1966, May 9.
  - STARK, [JEN], MRS. LOUIS
    - 1957, December 15.
  - SULZBERGER, ARTHUR HAYS (Publisher, N.Y. Times)
    - 1948, March 16.
    - 1954, December 30.
    - 1962, January 22.(reply to R.L.D.'s of Jan. 19, 1962 - Outgoing).
    - 1962, Sept. 18.
  - TOWNSEND, EARLE L. (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - 1942, September 29.re: R.L.D.'s leaving the Westport Defense Training Unit.
  - TRAILL, J. E.
    - 1958, Sept. 5.re: family history and Old John Duffus. With newsclip re: Williamstown Branch; business card; signature of J. W. Duffus, Burlington, Vt., April 14, 1886.
  - TRIGGS, A. B. (MRS. OSCAR LOVELL)
    - 1948, February 18.
  - WOLFF, MARIAN
    - n.d.
- MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - HUBBARD, Mrs. William B. (Cousin Elizabeth) to Ursula.
    - 1960, February 9.with note describing Cousin Elizabeth signed W.M.D. [Wm. M. Duffus?]
  - ROSS, Roland to Editor, N.Y. Times.
    - 1937, August 2.re: article by R.L.D.
  - SULZBERGER, ARTHUR HAYS to Mr. Gilmore D. Clark
    - 1960, January 4.re: editorial by R. L. D. - The Torch.
- LETTERS OF CONDOLENCE TO MRS. R. L. DUFFUS (Box 22, Folder 21)
  - Angell, Orson, 1972, Dec. 5
  - Bliven, Bruce, 1972, Nov. 30
  - Borland, Hal & Barbara, 1972, Dec. 1
  - Brockway, George P., 1972, Nov. 30
  - Chase, Stuart & Marian, [1972]
  - Chenery, William L., 1972, Dec. 6
  - Dodds, John W., 1972, Dec. 1
  - Gruening, Ernest, 1972, Nov. 30
  - Hough, Henry Beetle, 1972, Nov. 30
  - [Keyserling], Leon H., 1972, Dec. 12
  - Keyserling, Mary D[ublue], 1972, Dec. 4
  - McLeod, Rev. James W. 1972, Dec. 9 R.L.D. - In Appreciation with copy of N.Y. Times article by R.L.D.:I am an American.
  - Miller, Wm. F. 1972, Dec. 4(Vice Pres. & Provost- Stanford U.)
  - Oakes, John B., 1972, Dec. 9
  - Ogden, Wm. D., 1972, Nov, 30
  - O'Neill, Charles, 1972, Nov. 30
  - O'Neill, Charles, 1972, Dec. 13
  - Smith, Fletcher, 1973, Jan. 26
  - Sterling, J.E. Wallace, n.d.
  - Sulzberger, Iphigene Ochs, 1972, Dec. 2
    (Mrs. Arthur Hayes)
7/17/73
Names added to card file: new cards and additions
(* -signifies new card)
* Alphand, Herve
Anderson, Maxwell
Bliven, Bruce
* Brockway, George P.
Brooks, Van Wyck
Eisenhower, Dwight D.
* Gleason, Edgar T. (Scoop)
Keller, Helen
* LaGuardia, Fiorello H.
Older, Fremont
Sandburg, Carl
Sterling, J. E. Wallace
* Sulzberger, Arthur Hays